<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catascopos A surveigh and critique censure of the Christian world.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848626</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848626</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13735</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18153)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13735)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 642:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Catascopos A surveigh and critique censure of the Christian world.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>From the presse of William Stansby, and are to be sold by Iohn Smethwicke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13735:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13735:1"/>
            <p>Cataſcopos.</p>
            <p>A SVRVEIGH AND CRITIQVE CENSVRE OF THE CHRISTIAN WORLD.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Eſt cuivis rigidi facilis cenſura cachinni:</l>
               <l>Eſto. Ego fungoſae plebis ludibria ſperno.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON From the Preſſe of WILLIAM STANSBY, and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Smethwicke.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13735:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                  <l>Cum ſapiant pauci, paucis placuiſſe laboro,</l>
                  <l>Hoc tantum cupio, complacuiſſe bonis.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:2"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Suus cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> genius ſuum et ingenium.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>FAr from the turmoils of this worlds affairs,</l>
                  <l>Whence ſtill ſucceeding ſeas of endles woes,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Hydra's</hi> heads inflicting new deſpairs,</l>
                  <l>Conforund the ſoule with falſe deluding ſhowes:</l>
                  <l>In ſecret Cel, with ſweet content diuided,</l>
                  <l>I ſigh to ſee how mankind is miſguided.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Linquo Coax ranis, Ka coruis, vana<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> vanis:</l>
                     <l>Ad Logicam pergo quae mortis non timet ergo.</l>
                     <l>Hic vacue curis licet hic cantare ſub antro,</l>
                     <l>Et proculè speculo fluctus spectare furentes.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:3"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee great kings that mightie Septers ſwaie,</l>
                  <l>And take their vowes, the <hi>Gospel</hi> to protect:</l>
                  <l>Giue damned <hi>Atheiſme</hi> priuiledge and waie,</l>
                  <l>As though the <hi>Gospel</hi> were of none effect.</l>
                  <l>Yet is the <hi>Goſpel</hi> vnder foule diſguiſe,</l>
                  <l>Proclaimd the cauſe, whence Chriſtian wars ariſd.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Quicquid delirant reges plectuntur Achiui.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:3"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee how <hi>Moſes</hi> chaſt ſeat is deforn'd,</l>
                  <l>By brothel inceſt or adult'rous frie,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> pouertie haue ſcorn'd,</l>
                  <l>To glut themſelues with ſenſuall <hi>Sodomie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O age, wherein the Lamps that light ſhould ſhiue,</l>
                  <l>From vertue, truth and true zeale do decline!</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Domus mea domus orationis, &amp;c.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Optime hic ſuo fungitur officio, qui</l>
                     <l>ſtudet bene vivere.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:4"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee good lawes for godlie vſe diuiſed,</l>
                  <l>The iuſt mans right, and rigor for offenſes</l>
                  <l>By filthie lucre maſqued and diſguiſed.</l>
                  <l>Truth's but a ſound to ſhadow foule pretenſes:</l>
                  <l>For pride, ambition, ire and auarice</l>
                  <l>Do dull, dimme, blanch and blind the wiſeſt eies.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Pacis lex, legis ligamentum, iuſticia eſt.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:4"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee how wars, the <hi>Canker</hi> of Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Hels image and al common weales downthrow,</l>
                  <l>Spring from the proud ambitious harts debate,</l>
                  <l>Where rancor, ſpleene, and enuie ouerflow:</l>
                  <l>Not multitudes of men <hi>conqueſt</hi> atchieue:</l>
                  <l>Tis onely god that victorie doth giue.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Arma ira, vindicta<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Dei.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Fraterno primi maduerunt ſanguine fratres.</l>
                     <l>Fraterno primi maduerunt ſanguine muri.</l>
                     <l>Innocuo ſitiens ſanguine Romamadet.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:5"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee craft crept into the clowted ſhooe:</l>
                  <l>The ploughmans life that happie lifs diſgrac't,</l>
                  <l>Of yore content with fruits that did enſue</l>
                  <l>From feithful feilds, where al their hopes they plac't:</l>
                  <l>Now to the reſt I may it well reſemble.</l>
                  <l>Full taught to ſweare, forſweare, lie and diſſemble.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Foelix nimium prior aetas,</l>
                     <l>Contenta fidelibus arvis.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:5"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee extortion, and that boundleſſe gulf,</l>
                  <l>Hight vſury, which ſuck vp humane blood,</l>
                  <l>Deuouring lyue fleſh, like an hungrie woolf,</l>
                  <l>And vntill death, do neuer mite of good:</l>
                  <l>Where is old loue, which charitie men cleepe?</l>
                  <l>And where is conſcience? ſunck or ſound on ſleepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Divitis ad manes nil feret vmbra ſuos.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Dormierunt ſomnum ſuum, &amp; nihil invenerunt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iri divitiarum in manibus ſuis.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:6"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee in youth no reu'rence to old yeares,</l>
                  <l>Temples are made but marts to traffique in,</l>
                  <l>Regard to vertue but in feiwe appears,</l>
                  <l>Good works and almſdeeds are accompted ſinne:</l>
                  <l>Freindſhip is fled, and feithfull loue exiled,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sathan</hi> ſo much this laſt age hath beguiled.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>—heu dona bonorum</l>
                     <l>Sunt breuia, aeternum, quae nocuere, dolent.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:6"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee a ſect of Locuſts ſwarme of late,</l>
                  <l>That prie into ech <hi>Prince</hi> is Cabinet,</l>
                  <l>And rampe vpon the Maieſtie of ſtate,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſſaſſinats,</hi> though ſheepe they counterfet,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe proiect, is the worke of holy good,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe practize, poyſon, ſtrife, rebellion, bloud.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Quo, quo ſceleſti ruitis?</l>
                     <l>Furor ne coecus, an rapit vis acrior?</l>
                     <l>An culpa?</l>
                     <l>—culpa. vndi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tuto</l>
                     <l>Aſtutae vulpes penetrarunt viſcera regni.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:7"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee another ſect their oppoſite.</l>
                  <l>That leap beyond the limits of the lawe,</l>
                  <l>And perſonat the curious <hi>hipocrite,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of King and Church without reſpect or awe:</l>
                  <l>Inſtain'd with <hi>Phreſie,</hi> of neiw reformation,</l>
                  <l>That broach contempt, pride, peril, innouation.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Alter et alterius hoſtis, vter<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> nocet.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:7"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the true <hi>Euangiliques</hi> diſpos'd,</l>
                  <l>And held betwixt the is two extreams, at naught,</l>
                  <l>The one with foreigne ſtratagerns diſguiſd;</l>
                  <l>The other with domeſtique rancor fraught:</l>
                  <l>And both they, from their proper ends, conſpire,</l>
                  <l>To ſet all ſtates and king domes on a fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Peſtiferum mira propinant arte venenum,</l>
                     <l>Et miſer as blando circundant ore puellas.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:8"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the neſts, that nouriſh and maintaine</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>harpies,</hi> built in place of eminence:</l>
                  <l>Courts, Citie, groues hils, vallies and the plaine,</l>
                  <l>Shroud and ſupport their vncurbd inſolence:</l>
                  <l>☞ The Centinels, that ſhould the feilds defend,</l>
                  <l>As Scar-crowes, but amaze, but not amend.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Nihil intereſt, faueas ne ſceleri,</l>
                     <l>an illud facias.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:8"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee a <hi>Chaos</hi> of the vniuers,</l>
                  <l>Religion, laws, minds, maners, tongues tranform'd,</l>
                  <l>Whilom the direct current, now reuers,</l>
                  <l>The Luſtre of the holy place deform'd,</l>
                  <l>☞ Where ſin doth ſit and ſwaie the ſtedles helme:</l>
                  <l>Whiles <hi>Schiſme</hi> &amp; ſects poore vertue ouerwhelme.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Tempora temporibus ſuccumbunt prima futuris.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:9"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee that triple mitred monſters head</l>
                  <l>Gilt with the gores of ſacred maieſtie,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Altans</hi> Ore with guiltleſſe blood be ſpred,</l>
                  <l>But that's not all, O vnhard butcheries!</l>
                  <l>He lookt of late, at one blow, to deuoure</l>
                  <l>A King, Queene, Prince, and kingdom in an houre.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Stat cruor in templis, multa<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> rubentia caede</l>
                     <l>Lubrica ſaxa madent, nulli ſua profuit aetas,</l>
                     <l>Non genus aut ſexus.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:9"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee, O God! and muſt I hold my peace?</l>
                  <l>Are not the liues of Kings and Princes deere?</l>
                  <l>Will heere, thinke you, their rabious furie ceaſe?</l>
                  <l>No, no, moe plots in practice are, I feare.</l>
                  <l>☞ Let Iacob know, no true peace to enioy,</l>
                  <l>When Aegypt ſtill affronts him with annoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Incauta ſemper nimia praeſumptio eſt</l>
                     <l>&amp; ſui negligens.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:10"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the Bees, whoſe feithfull zeale inclin'd,</l>
                  <l>Their hiues with waxe and hony to replet,</l>
                  <l>By ſlothfull drons confronted and confin'd,</l>
                  <l>That ſucke the ſweet, for which they neuer ſwet:</l>
                  <l>But hog-like francke and feed their glottonie,</l>
                  <l>Whiles their poore flock vnſed and famiſht lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Dat veniam coruis, vexat cenſura columbas.</l>
                     <l>—et ſic</l>
                     <l>Infoelix lolium, ſteriles dominantur auenae.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:10"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the cureles <hi>Gangren</hi> that inſect.</l>
                  <l>And mortifies the bodies ſoundeſt part,</l>
                  <l>Diſperſe it ſelfe with dangerous affects,</l>
                  <l>Through al the veines, to ſeize vpon the hart:</l>
                  <l>And yet I ſee not art nor policie,</l>
                  <l>Giue rupture to that mortall malidie.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Aditum nocendi, perſido preſtat fides.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Opprime, dum nous ſunt, ſubitimala ſemina morbi,</l>
                     <l>Antidotus cinerinam ſua ſera venit.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:11"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee examples, that teach to be wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Remote, and of too recent memorie,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe yet hoat blood, aſcended to the skies,</l>
                  <l>Call for reueinge, but held as dreams; and why?</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Sirens</hi> ſongs doe lul our ſenſe ſleepe</l>
                  <l>Our dogs are dead, wolfs ouerrun the ſheepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Fiſtula dulce canit, voluorom dum decipit auteps,</l>
                     <l>Corda<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> foedifragum mortaliae faſcinat aurum.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:11"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the two forerunners of the fall</l>
                  <l>And period of Eſtats and Monarchies,</l>
                  <l>Venting their venim blancht with ſugred gall,</l>
                  <l>Two fatal Siſters Pride and Luxuries:</l>
                  <l>That with their vnknown ſtrange effects portend,</l>
                  <l>Or woe, or wracke or ruine in the end.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Luxus &amp; ſuperbia non aegrotae modo,</l>
                     <l>Sed periclitantis reipublicae inditia.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:12"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee all ſinnes haue aeſta's height or'e paſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſwel at ful with <hi>Autums</hi> ſurcharg'd wonder,</l>
                  <l>Expecting that both ſyth and ſickle haſt,</l>
                  <l>To cut the proud apoſtum'd bulke in ſunder:</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Sodom-like Rhamun ſia</hi> do coſume,</l>
                  <l>Boulk, ſtuble, flraw &amp; chaffe with quenchles fume.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Grandia ſupplicijs grauibus peccata luuntur.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:12"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the Eagles in confined eie</l>
                  <l>To toure about the earth's inheritance,</l>
                  <l>Scorning all birds that would him timber bye,</l>
                  <l>To interrupt his ſelfe ſole gouernance:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſublim'd thoughts which no meane can conteine,</l>
                  <l>Shall know, 'gainſt God, mans counſels are but vaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Quicquid in altum fortuna tulit, tuitur a leuat.</l>
                     <l>Depoſuit potentes de ſede ſua, &amp;c.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:13"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the glorious Churches of the Eaſt,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſplendor long time, till of late had ſhin'd,</l>
                  <l>Now by the common enemie poſſeſt.</l>
                  <l>Shal home-bred diſcord ſtil our Iudgements blin'da</l>
                  <l>And ſhall our ſelfs be ſtirs-men to our woe?</l>
                  <l>I ſay no more, God graunt it be not ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Propter iniquitatem populi transferetur</l>
                     <l>regnum de gente in gentens.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:13"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee, and what? O ſee, but ſight no more,</l>
                  <l>To weepe or laugh were paſſions, bootles, vaine.</l>
                  <l>Compute the ſcaſons that haue paſt before;</l>
                  <l>From peace to wars, from wars to peace againe:</l>
                  <l>And thou ſhalt ſay, it is decreed from <hi>hie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Times haue their turns, aske not <hi>Iehouah</hi> why.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Mundus ſemper ſibi ſimilis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Currunt sic ordi ne f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
                     <l>Rotat omnia fatum.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13735:14"/>
               <head>Cataſcopos.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cogita ſuper nos, O Deus, cogitationes pacis &amp; non afflictionis, &amp; des finem &amp; patientiam, &amp; inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabimus te, &amp; viuemus. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic"> Verbum Domini manet in aternum.</q>
               <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic"> —non me<lb/> Falſus honos iuuat, aut
<list>
                     <item>mordax</item>
                     <item>mendax</item>
                  </list> infamia terret.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13735:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
